[Music]
thank you
hello and welcome everyone this is
active live stream number 49.1
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
the Institute and how to get involved in
projects such as the live streams and
others
okay
we are here in live stream number 49.1
we are having our second discussion on
the paper a worked example of the
Bayesian mechanics of classical objects
in number 49.0 along with Jacob and Ali
we did some backgrounds and context and
now the gloves come off the curtain
comes up
uh
and we'll begin slash continue our
discussion
and we're really appreciative Dalton
that you've joined today
looking forward to how these discussions
go so we can begin just by saying hello
and anything that we want to explore or
discuss today
and then we'll just jump right into it
so I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California
and I
think some of the questions that are
really motivating me today is what is
mechanical about Bayesian mechanics and
how do we take Concepts that have
physical
interpretations like center of gravity
or even some of these more Atomic level
terms that were brought into play
how do we apply those kinds of terms and
ideas to cognitive science and I'll pass
to ollie
hello I'm Ali I'm an independent
researcher from Iran and I can't find
enough words to express how excited I am
to be here uh actually we talk a lot
about uh Dalton's work and how
groundbreaking it is and personally I
had immersed myself for the past several
months in Dalton's paper and for the
past couple of months we had fascinating
discussions around this particular paper
so I'm feeling kind of StarStruck right
now and I'm very much looking forward to
our discussion and I'll pass it to yacob
hello I'm jakub I'm a student in the UK
and
uh
I suppose
um also uh very uh very excited to to be
here today and to discuss the different
implications of Bayesian mechanics and
how uh how it's related to other areas
in contemporary physics and how that can
then be applied to cognitive sciences
and Neuroscience
awesome so welcome thanks again Dalton
feel free to just
begin where you'd like and bring us to
the paper
of course yeah um I guess I'll I'll also
introduce uh myself just in case uh
there are people in the audience that
don't recognize me or uh have a face to
a name
um I'm Dalton uh I'm a researcher I'm
based at um Stony Brook University in
New York uh where I spend most of my
time in the Department of Mathematics
and the department of physics and
astronomy I'm also at the verses lab uh
where I'm I'm the mathematics and the
physics of the free energy principle
um so it's it's a pleasure to meet uh
all three of you uh and and thank you of
course for the kind words
um I think we can yeah maybe begin with
uh very broad overview of the paper I
will say um so one of my
um one of the aims of my research
program uh is to get a better
understanding of the mathematics of
um random dynamical systems especially
coupled random dynamical systems or
um systems that model uh non-equilibria
uh phenomena and one of the interesting
things to me
is the idea that uh within cognitive
science or Neuroscience there are some
algorithms that have been developed over
time that uh I have been built
specifically to cope with these kinds of
problems
um which are problems that we don't know
really how to make sense of
mathematically even physically
um where on the uh back foot
um
but in uh in Neuroscience then the
primary object of study is a
um
non-equilibrium system it is
non-equilibria and understanding
non-equilibrium phenomena in the brain
and so one supposes that the methods
that have been developed over time in
this area uh just maybe by trial and
error
um or at least trial and error by the
standards of perhaps a pure
mathematician uh may have some insights
into maths and physics in the same way
that there's a very rich history of
physics uh inspiring more advanced
mathematics and then mathematics
circling back and making physics more
rigorous I think there's a great
opportunity to do that in biophysical
systems and I think the free energy
principle is a source of great
inspiration along those lines
so uh with that meta commentary out of
the way
um one of the things that I I wanted to
do with this paper is to actually drill
down on that point uh because I think
it's something that uh maybe Gets Lost
in Translation if you just read uh kind
of traditional active inference papers
that are all about modeling cognition I
think there is there's something on the
other side of the aisle to be said about
what do those models of cognition say
about modeling systems that are
cognitive or what does it say about
complex systems that are cognitive like
and how can we make sense of those
things mathematically so that's that's
in some uh sense the motivation for
basic mechanics and that goes back to
what goes back a long time
um it goes back to probably
um Carl himself he mentions something
like this at a couple of points in the
uh 2019 monograph but um it was worth
writing a paper specifically with the
motivation that uh
if we consider what's been written about
the free energy principle so far there's
a very nice foundation for a better
understanding the mathematics and
physics of coupled or non-equilibrium
sarcastic processes and so that was the
the motivation for this particular paper
and
um in addition to building out the
fundamental mathematics in the first few
sections uh it's then possible to
contextualize all that work with a kind
of nice work example of what does this
mean for some kind of simple systems how
can we actually take this foundational
maths and make it algorithmic again and
then foreshadowing maybe even greater
complexity in in the very last section
uh so yes a lot of this goes back to a
paper that um I co-authored with a
number of other people uh earlier in the
summer called on Bayesian mechanics uh
where it's it's proposed that you know
complex systems have a kind of
informational physics about them and
that maybe the material physics or the
the Maths for these systems
um is quite challenging in general but
maybe if you map these systems into the
informational world you can utilize new
techniques and make sense of these kinds
of systems uh by approaching it from a
different kind of viewpoint that is I
think the the strength of basic
mechanics as again Carl and others have
construed it is it is a way of talking
about informational physics or the
physics of Bayesian beliefs uh the laws
of motion on a statistical manifold
various ways of of kind of couching that
in more formal language but again that
was the motivation for the paper and
then uh as that gets developed
eventually there's a point where we
really get into the trenches and
actually try and deploy this in some
useful way I think that those are really
the the kind of two aims that come
together in some sense
thank you for the summary
well there's many ways to begin and
start perhaps we could start with the
context that we brought which was
thinking about this and you touched on
some of these threads as well
such as the key literature and some of
the history
let's continue on in this context
setting before we get to the formalisms
and the worked examples and talk about
the three kinds of theories including
what you mean by a theory and then the
three non-bayesian mechanics and that'll
set us up really well to see where
Bayesian mechanics comes into play
so this was in that paper just mentioned
on Bayesian mechanics a physics of and
by beliefs so what are dynamics
mechanics and principles and how were
you using Theory and why was it so
important to be clear about what a
theory was and the distinctions amongst
these three terms
yeah of course um so in in that paper
there is this kind of trichotomy that
gets introduced uh where we talk uh both
about Dynamics and mechanics and
principles and and disentangle them in a
very particular way
um so we we think about Dynamics as a
kind of observational thing
and it's important to separate that from
mechanics because uh complex systems
as a science is very interested in
Dynamics can I kind of infer the laws of
these kinds of systems just by modeling
them
um using some kind of curve fitting or
using some kind of set of canonical
models that I know sort of sits uh fits
this situation but but at the end of the
day yes Dynamics are mostly
um about the particular trajectories
that a system takes through State space
or physical space
um and and this is
uh conflated sometimes with what I call
mechanics in that paper which is
um something a little bit different it
is the laws from which these
trajectories are determined and so um
for instance uh dynamical systems people
especially in pure maths really like the
example of Billiards so you uh you send
one Billet ball crashing into another
one and and you could
um talk about the trajectory that the uh
ball takes and and you could write down
the equations of motion
um for this system
and just add up all the forces acting on
it and figure out what direction is this
uh the ball that got collided with what
direction is that going to go into uh
with what momentum and all of these
things but then
figuring out
um those figuring out that trajectory
once you plug in all of these uh kind of
boundary conditions the mass of the ball
the angle of the initial contact and and
so forth
um the way that you can kind of compose
all that information together that needs
to come from somewhere and that's what
we call uh or what I call a mechanical
principle and this is not a distinction
that is new to literature like I'm not
breaking new ground here but I think uh
it
is one of those things that's not made
sufficiently clear in the fep literature
uh or at least in the um physical uh the
places where it's adjacent to physics so
mechanics are about the laws that give
you those trajectories so we know that
that the force is acting on one or
another uh billiard balls some together
because of Newton's law of motion that's
a mechanical theory if I have F then I
get M times a and I can plug in F and I
can plug in a and I can get a trajectory
but if I abstract away from those
particulars I get some kind of law that
tells me okay how a trajectories
generated in the physical world
um abstracting one more step we can then
ask okay so where do mechanical theories
come from what tells me that I have the
right mechanical Theory generating the
right Dynamics and this is about
um
the kinds of very fundamental laws that
we know hold everywhere in the universe
at a given scale these are principles
like conservation of energy and this
gives you uh the behavior of collisions
or the principle of stationary action
which actually gives you back Newton's
law so you can now chain these things
together and say the you know one ball
hits the other one it goes in this
direction uh because uh if you sum the
forces and you add up all the directions
you get a net movement and you can do
that because uh these uh Billet balls
minimize or at least make stationary uh
their action so their motion must follow
this particular mechanical law and
that's the law that generates these
trajectories so the reason why this is
mentioned in the Bayesian mechanics
papers because these have I think been
conflated in the literature previously
because you have
um
the idea of the free energy principle
which is a principle it's a thing that
gives you back
um some kind of generative uh rule for
the Dynamics of specific systems and uh
that is usually something to do with the
motion of internal States on a
statistical manifold in the sense of for
instance uh Thomas Parr lands to cast
and Carl Kristen's article
um stochastic thermodynamics Markov
blankets and information geometry
I think that's the title anyway
um so if you if you say okay the the
Dynamics of a system whose parameter
performs
um approximate phase in inference uh
minimizes the surprisal
then you get approximate base in
inference as a law of motion for the
Dynamics of some object and this law is
usually written as a particular gradient
flow relation on uh the space of beliefs
so it tells you how do beliefs change as
those parameters doing the inference
change and then if you if you add in
progressively more details okay what do
those internal States actually mean in
the context of the system what are those
beliefs about these are the kind of
boundary conditions that give you the
trajectories the specific dynamics of
the system there's an interesting sense
in which these boundary conditions are
literal boundary conditions because
understanding what's internal and what's
external and being inferred is precisely
the specification of a Markov blanket so
as soon as you actually give the system
a very particular partition as soon as
you've carve it up in a specific way you
start to get a sense of the actual
evolution of a system as one might see
it in the real world but this is I think
separating things out in a formal sense
like this is useful because it avoids
skipping from step one which is minimize
variation of free energy or surprisal
and I'm going straight away to this is
how
um something like an active inference
system uh does prediction and action you
know there's there are some steps in the
middle that hadn't really been filled
out if you just go from A to B directly
and when you when you begin to talk
about the maths and the physics
um
collapsing things together like that
starts to throw away some important
details that actually do make a
difference in the way that you tell the
story
Awesome Ali or Jacob anything you want
to add in or ask there
yeah Jacob
um yeah I would maybe ask regarding the
kind of laws of motion of Bayesian
mechanics you mentioned uh approximate
Bayesian inference uh would would that
imply that the 3D faces of Bayesian
mechanics the mode matching mode
tracking and path tracking uh would you
say those are also specific Laws of
Motion within Bayesian mechanics
um you you could say that yeah I think
at this point the distinction gets uh
very fine and and so there's there is a
place to usefully truncate it but yeah
these These are three different kinds of
approximate Bayesian inference
um and so uh they are three different uh
kinds of motion under free energy
principle minimization
um and so this is kind of I guess a
middle area between Dynamics and
mechanics you've started to specify some
things like am I doing approximate
Bayesian inference Over States or am I
doing it over paths but you're still
lacking actual dynamical details about
what do those states of paths mean
um so this is maybe this is maybe a
middle area that that blends the idea of
approximate Bayesian inference as a law
of motion under surprise minimization
and actually getting down to the very
bottom of this um pyramid so if I were
to put it somewhere into this figure I'd
I'd maybe slotted in uh yeah uh yeah
that's that's pretty much what I'm
imagining is you have approximate
Bayesian inference sort of roughly up
here and then there are different
expressions of that just as there are
different expressions of Newton's Laws
depending on if you're in fluids or
rigid bodies or Celestial mechanics so
you can introduce even finer partitions
than these three
there's many places to go
one question is what are these modes
about who or what is tracking what and
when
yeah so this is uh kind of about
um
the idea being a proxy of Bayesian
inference tells you that systems match
their parameters in such a way that they
perform inference right so when we think
about Bayesian inference we can talk
about it as simply inferring the
parameters of a probability density
uh so in the free energy principle
um when you get approximate Bayesian
inference uh saying okay systems that
are coupled synchronize uh certain
parameters this is Bayesian inference
um and and conversely if you have that
synchronization you have Bayesian
inference or you have approximate
Bayesian inference if you're inferring
the parameters of an approximate density
which is where you get into the uh
factorization of the free energy
functional that we uh are familiar with
where you have
um a variational density matched to a
joint density but you can split it into
the variational density matched to a
conditional density plus an extra
surprisal term that uh kind of measures
how good that approximation is
um so this this descends from that idea
that you can deduce what a system is
doing
um just by saying okay it's performing a
proximate Bayesian inference because
that allows you to say its parameters
are synchronizing to the parameters of
the environment or of another system
um so that's what we mean when we say uh
modes in this case a mode is just a
parameter of the distribution and it
comes from
um some of uh Carl's earlier literature
where uh he uses the LaPlace
approximation so uh specifically we're
matching the we're kind of fitting a
gaussian density to some arbitrary
probability and then the uh mode of that
gaussian is one of the parameters
because it tells you okay where is the
center of that density and if you also
get a sense of where the variance of
that density is now suddenly um by
fitting those two parameters you can
talk about the system because now you
can say okay the physical parameters of
the system are encoding these parameters
of some density uh in in a very natural
way this gets you back much of
statistical physics because it's all
about how does a system reflect these
statistics of another system
probabilistically how does this look but
this is kind of upgraded in Bayesian
mechanics to noting that well that
inference happens because the physical
parameters of the system are matching
the physical parameters of the
environment and and that's where the
probabilities come from that's why we
talk about beliefs so when we say modes
we're referring to
um parameters that are fit for
synchronization
excellent thank you Jacob
um since uh we have the the schema on
the on the slide there I uh just wanted
to ask where do you think that the G
Theory
um formulation uh fits into this diagram
because with the G Theory there is
approximate Bayesian inference but uh
it's not necessarily density Over States
so is it another uh another node from
directly from the Bayesian mechanics
yeah
um so in this um figure the approximate
Bayesian inference Lemma is a very
specific thing it that originally goes
back to I believe originally it's in a
2012 paper by Carl in in entropy called
the free energy principle for biological
systems but but um certainly it's a much
bigger deal is made uh in the 2019
monograph and and it's it's the
approximate Bayesian inference Lemma as
he calls it specifically about mode
matching approximate base and inference
is a bit more General so if you were to
kind of slot that in somewhere in here
it would maybe be parallel to Bayesian
mechanics because just like classical
mechanics the law of motion is Newton's
laws for basic mechanics the law of
motion the thing that generates specific
physical Dynamics is approximate
Bayesian inference or the the law that
when you do have synchronized systems
you can write it as variational free
energy minimization
in virtue of the parameters of the two
systems matching up and and that's the
parameter that minimizes the distance
between a health density and an observed
density so approximately inference Lemma
is is that result specifically but
that's more General the idea of
approximate Bayesian inference is more
General and probably
um
someone needs to write down a
generalization of the approximate phase
in infants Lemma to paths specifically
to talk about path tracking but once you
have a path that fits the bill as a mode
and once you have two systems evolving
together tracking each other's modes or
each other's paths and if you have a
probability density over those paths you
can now talk about approximate Bayesian
inference in the path setting now where
that has to do with G Theory uh so so G
Theory the the name and and kind of the
vision is actually due to uh Maxwell
ramstead a colleague of mine also here
in the verses lab
and uh he has suggested that
um G Theory kind of lies in the
intersection between a few different
things that fall out of the path-based
formalism so if you have
um a process of Bayesian inference over
paths if you're doing uh path tracking
um then there are lots of things that do
come out of this uh almost canonically
one of them is uh everything that comes
along with path integral formulations in
quantum mechanics and and this is uh I
take advantage of this at various points
in the paper at one point I I use it to
explain okay why does spacing mechanics
actually make sense in the classical
world and then later on I use it to
relate it to chaos
um that's a specific example I think
more generally uh path tracking deals
with non-stationary systems very well uh
because you're allowed to talk about now
how does the density uh how does the
belief change in time how does the mode
of a single belief change over time to
make a kind of uh modal path and and
what are the marginals if you slice up
the density along that path um what do
you get so you can talk about
non-stationary systems you can talk
about systems out of equilibrium this
way because you can relate
um
the uh free energy principle over paths
to What's called the principle of
Maximum caliber in statistical physics
which is all about non-equilibria and uh
entry production and non-equilibrium
steady States uh so so I think um
as as we have written about it
um G theory is the
uh Duality between path integrals and
the fep over paths or The Duality
between Max Cal and maximum caliber and
and the fep overpaths but it's um
I think that's selling it short a little
bit because it it's also the thing that
brings in all these other uh ideas
um and stochastic thermodynamics is a
really interesting one as well right
also falls out of the path-based
formulas and very well also does very
well with um non-equilibria
um
so so G theory is kind of this this
larger object that uh makes sense of why
that column of Bayesian mechanics
actually works uh and and explains a
little of the the true power of uh the
path tracking as opposed to uh mode
tracking why why are we interested in
forgetting about States uh and and
that's the explanation for that uh or
the justification for that uh resides in
G Theory which is supposed to explain uh
why do all of these things just come out
of the path based formalism why does it
make sense
um and why does the fep overpass lie at
the center of a lot of disparate fields
which I think is one of the real um very
powerful statements uh that that may be
possible in the near future is uh is the
fep actually canonically the theory of
everything in the sense that there are
lots of approaches in uh statistical
physics and stochastic process theory
that Trace back to the fep or the fep uh
subsumes or implies or something like
this G theory is supposed to kind of
plug into that last column uh but but
it's somewhat outside the hierarchy in
that sense
foreign
thank you Ali
uh well yeah uh I was uh
um
when I was reading about G Theory uh I
thought it somehow relates to uh Rolf
Lander's principle which basically says
that uh if an observer loses information
about a system uh the corresponding
entropy in a non-information bearing uh
degrees of freedom of the information
processing system or its environment is
increased uh because uh you know London
landar believed that information is
physical so he somehow put it in terms
of a kind of thermodynamical uh point of
view but
um how does it fit or can G Theory be
viewed through the lens of
landor's principle which I think is not
a um completely non-controversial
Principle as well
yeah that's an interesting question I
think uh insofar as it does give you
some technology to talk about entry
production at non-equilibrium steady
state so so it does give you a way of
saying okay if I'm exchanging with my
environment if information is Flowing
out and flowing back in then there is
some increase in the entropy and with
respect to things like control theory
this is pretty interesting because it
allows you to talk about okay if the
system is observing something about its
environment if it's constantly
um
maintaining a steady state so engaging
in control then then you can talk about
that and tropically and you can talk
about the irreversibility of processes
even at steady state
um and and there are you know there are
things that connect to that like um
the crooks uh fluctuation theorem or
yazinski equality and things of that
nature
um so so my guess would be uh it it
probably covers something like landau's
principle in that context
um talking about the the energy required
to erase a bit of information so is
ultimately the energy required to
insulate yourself from the environment
that that minimizes your surprisal it
means the environment does not offer
information to you but but that does
take energy and and sometimes quite a
lot uh so so that's that's probably
where that
um connects to London's principle is
talking about and quantifying
um the the kind of cost of maintaining a
Markov blanket uh in in probably
entropic terms
great I think this points towards
somewhere we may explore over this
multi-scale engagement which is
unconventional Computing and low energy
Computing for example the often remarked
upon energy expenditure of the brain
compared to say a neural network
operating on traditional computational
architectures using many many light
bulbs many many calories of energy
versus the brain which able uh which is
able to carry out some tasks with
seemingly low energy expenditure while
other tasks it does not seem to be able
to perform at all
I want to pull back
before we go into the three non-bayesian
mechanics and ask what is Bayesian
what does it mean for something to be
Bay Bayesian
yeah um in in my mind
um Bayesian is about uh inference it's
about a particular method of doing
inference that gives you a consistent
unbiased results and fits in very nicely
with the rest of probability Theory
uh in the context of Bayesian mechanics
it is the idea that uh the physics of
material systems or the material physics
of complex systems Maps into a physics
of beliefs so you can talk about the
parameters that are doing approximate
Bayesian inference or you can talk about
approximate phase and inference you can
talk about okay what what are the
beliefs parameterized by that mode doing
and how does that reflect something
about the Dynamics of the system
um the reason why this is interesting is
not just because it's a different
approach to the problem
and dealing with
um interacting systems and uh systems
out of equilibrium uh is an area that
does need new approaches because it is a
very poorly understood area within
mathematics and physics uh it still is
it has been for uh some time I think
uh but um it's also interesting because
uh complex systems are informational so
there's there's some sense in which this
brings us closer to the metal
um so it's not just a new view it is the
right New View because complex systems
are systems that compute and capture
data
um they are systems that have memory
um so it's it's not as simple as even
here's a new way of writing down the
Dynamics of random uh or stochastic
processes uh based on the
parameterization of some action
functional that's that's valuable
because that's a new thing but it's also
uh it fits very nicely into our
understanding of complex systems as
things that uh have an informational
physics understanding the Dynamics of
things like the brain is contingent upon
understanding what the brain is doing
and and the brain is uh capturing and
Computing over data it is storing
memories it is learning and sensing and
inferring so
it's it's not just that it's a new view
it's really the Right View because it
gets to the idea that complex systems do
things physically
because they are doing something in
informational space and and the brain is
a wonderful example of that the brain is
a coupled random dynamical system it's
coupled to its environment so you can
talk about this parameterization thing
this synchronization thing but it's it's
even more insightful than just that
because the brain is
um doing approximate Bayesian inference
so so I suppose it's no coincidence that
the synchronization of couple ground and
dynamical systems gets you back this
idea
um because I think that is
empirically just based on observations I
think that is as close to a physical law
as one might be able to get at this
stage in complex systems theory is that
things that synchronize do perform a
proxy base in inference because things
that synchronize are things that are
controlled systems or computational
systems uh so so in that sense it's I
think it's right on the mark
and and as I said you know it's it's
interesting that this goes way back to
trying to figure out things about the
brain
uh it goes way back to to Carl friston's
original work on generalized filtering
and SPM and and these kinds of
algorithms that were designed to make
sense of what is the brain doing
physically based on what we think it's
doing inferentially right the
relationship between structural and
functional connectivity and the
relationship between neural
representations and neural firing
patterns but it has become something
massively more General because it is the
right kind of maths to talk about these
sorts of systems and that's in turn
because these sorts of systems do
um this kind of approximate Bayesian
inference uh so when when you ask yeah
what is babysitting about basic
mechanics it is about the relationship
between Bayesian beliefs and and
Bayesian inference uh and physical
parameters representing something about
the information available uh to that
system uh or the statistics of a system
coupled to that system
awesome just a few notes before we then
go into the non-basing mechanics one is
from ecological psychology where many of
our terms are drawn from such as
affordances people have long pointed to
the way that we use language like can
you grasp it optimal grasp of ideas and
so tangible and peripersonal spatial
ways of talking about ideas and
cognitive processes and then well what
is the first thing you want to know
after you get optimal grasp how much
does it weigh and you said it has become
massively more General well is that in
grams or in what so I see this as part
of the development of the physicality of
cognition in that the ecological
psychology brought in relationality
and action orientation the pragmatic
turn
and then now what about those objects if
we drop the idea what happens if we drop
it from the discussion what happens
um and then the second piece is the very
interesting historical note about the
development of complex systems
and about the appropriateness of this
kind of a formalism
because at the very least standing as
extremely on the instrumental Spectrum
as we can be we're going to need to bake
relationality into our analysis of any
system whatever it is that it is doing
and then absolutely it may come to be
the case that if those systems are also
cognitive or understood in terms of
informational manifolds
then it's a doubly appropriate approach
and the kind of double ratcheting
of cognition
makes it difficult to see how a
framework that doesn't have some of
these characteristics could be adequate
to describe that kind of a relation
so great points
let us go to the non-bayesian mechanics
so
the non-basing mechanics
are classical statistical and quantum
so however you'd like maybe just uh on
each of the following three slides just
what are classical mechanics statistical
mechanics and quantum mechanics uh kind
of Steel personing the argument and just
what do they explain what will they
continue to be useful for and how can we
see them as special cases or adjacencies
or however you'd like to frame it with
respect to basic mechanics
sure
um yeah so beginning with um classical
mechanics I think is probably the
um simplest example
um you have kind of the physics of very
large very slow things large is kind of
a relative term large compared to atoms
maybe and slow compared to the speed of
light but nonetheless
um this is a a broad region of physics
that describes uh things that don't have
relativistic effects uh things where
observations commute so it's non-quantum
things that are not noisy so there's no
probabilities it's not statistical and
things that do not require relatives to
Corrections so things that are below the
speed of light
um
when you have all four of those
ingredients I think I listed four anyway
you have classical uh physics uh or at
least you have a classical object and
the physics of that thing
um is classical mechanics uh so this
um this arises from uh you may have in
the third four limits of other kinds of
physics so you want to be uh now
infinitely precise
um so this is the kind of no noise limit
of statistical mechanics it's these slow
speeds limit of um special relativity uh
and and it's a very interesting
um limit of quantum mechanics that I can
get into a little bit but it's it begins
to get a bit complicated
um I I maybe I'll save that for the the
third slide
um so yes but but uh until then I'll say
you you there is a classical limit of
quantum mechanics that you take a
Quantum field Theory and and you can
produce a classical Theory out of that
in a relatively well-defined way
um and and again I can talk a little
about the nuances to that statement
there are some but but regardless
um classical physics is about
um
large things really the the interesting
thing is that all four of these limits
kind of coincide
um to some extent when you have a
very large uh system
so very large systems allow you to use
the law of large numbers to kind of
sharpen your beliefs about a system so
so you can imagine this as placing
greater Precision on the measurement of
your of your system and and that
recreates sort of the the no noise limit
because you get more and more precise in
your estimate of the Dynamics of the
system
um many uh body systems with very small
objects
um are systems where you start to see
Quantum Productions so particles uh like
atomic particles for instance
um you begin to run into uh things a
regime where things are small enough
that quantum physics becomes relevant
um
and also uh large systems tend to move
pretty slowly that is just a general
rule um in in what's called effective
field Theory which talks about how one
theory is a limit of another theory and
in particular it talks about as you
increase in scale you get simpler
theories so I think we would probably
all agree classical physics is a lot
simpler than quantum physics and that's
because effective field Theory says that
um large things uh have simpler physics
in in very rigorous uh senses one
expression of that is
um kind of uh the momentum scale is
inverse to the mass scale so larger
things generally have lower momentum
lower energy very small things whiz
around at very fast speeds they have
high momentum
um
so once you once you start to talk about
large systems things begin simplifying
in such a way that more often than not
you run into classical physics as a
sufficient description of the scale of
observation that you're at
uh so so classical physics um that's
where it comes from uh it is about
um Newton's law uh classical mechanics
Newtonian mechanics as you might call it
is about Newton's law it says uh that
well Newton's three laws I suppose I
should say
um they say that uh
the um every action has an equal and
opposite reaction
um so this is the idea that things that
uh make so contact forces uh have at the
classical level an equivalent force in
the opposite direction
um you can think of this as a kind of uh
if you're familiar with them
sort of exercise
exercises in school
um in this area you're often asked to
calculate the normal force of something
um the normal force is just what pushes
up on me when I push down on something
else so this is why I don't uh phase
through the ground when I stand up is
because there is an equal and opposite
reaction I'm not only putting a force on
the ground but the ground is acting on
me and keeping me up
um
that's that's one of them uh the other
one is the very famous f equals n a it
says that uh the force acting on a
system uh is the mass times the
acceleration of the system and likewise
you can deduce the acceleration of a
system by taking the force acting on it
and dividing out the mass
um so this this tells you okay how do we
generate Dynamics out of some boundary
conditions like what is the mass what
direction is the force acting in
and and classical mechanics comes from a
what we call least action principle and
there are a number of equivalent ways of
writing this
um but this generalizes to uh what some
people call lagrangian mechanics and
that tells you
um
imagining what are the energies that
those forces came from
how does the system behave with respect
to its energies and and if you talk
about stationary action you talk about
minimizing energy then you can recover
Newton's Laws as a system accelerates
along Force gradients and and it doesn't
waste energy by going any faster or
going any slower it does exactly what
it's told to do so it uses precisely the
energy budget available to it there's a
very nice
um well maybe I should say about my own
paper but there's a very lengthy
exposition of this in the uh physics of
and by beliefs paper that we've talked
about once already I think it's section
two where I run through
um why is the analogy the classical
mechanics even useful here and it's
because of
um the stuff that we talked about
previously with the very nice dichotomy
or trichotomy between principles
mechanics and Dynamics
um but uh anyway more broadly uh than
that classical mechanics is a very good
example of a least action principle
because it's the idea that the Dynamics
of classical things comes from a
particular uh scale appropriate limiting
um least action principle
excellent
Ali or Jacob anything to add or we'll
move to statistical mechanics
okay
classical descriptions
onto statistical
yeah so statistical mechanics is uh
a bit of an interesting one
statistical mechanics is a lot broader
than I think
uh one might initially think
because at the end of the day it is to
some extent just about systems with as
you've written here probabilistic
degrees of freedom and and that is
that covers a lot of things you know you
can probability theory is just maths so
any way you can use probability Theory
to describe
um some system you can use statistical
mechanics and we know that this is
the this generality does exist because
you can talk about
um Quantum statistical mechanics so you
can take the physics of very small very
fast things and and use statistical
mechanical methods you can use
probability Theory and entropy in these
things and you can also go all the way
up to uh black hole thermodynamics and
you can do the same you can talk if it's
a black holes of very large things
um and but you can still talk about the
thermodynamics or statistical mechanics
of black holes so it's it's worth saying
that um
we can talk about the uh no noise limit
of a particular kind of statistical
mechanics but then we need to be a
little bit more precise about what that
generates
um
in this case I'm thinking of classical
statistical mechanics so it's the
statistical mechanics of
um interacting particles or uh systems
with microstates
that relate to macro states by uh some
kind of Gibbs relation
and things that have free energy and and
in particular Shannon entropy so this is
a little bit more of a narrower idea of
what statistical mechanics is
um just because we we need to constrain
ourselves a little bit even to get off
the ground so otherwise we'd be covering
um way too much but it is the case that
if you take statistical descriptions of
um
ensembles of objects and you become more
and more precise and you get rid of the
noise then you can reproduce a kind of
classical equations of motion
um
and there are ways of doing that uh one
such thing is called mean field Theory
so in mean field Theory you get rid of
the noise in a system and you just say
okay here is the trajectory of the
system uh in the same way as we might do
with uh classical mechanics
um I'm skipping some details there and
the analogy is a little bit more nuanced
than that but it's it's kind of a useful
mental picture I think
um and one of the interesting things to
note I think is as what you've written
here is that there is a principle that's
relevant for statistical mechanics
um because uh statmac is very general
it's very mathematical it requires an
equally mathematical principle
um and so in a probability Theory we
have What's called the maximum entropy
principle which is just a way of
Designing probability densities around
uh
inferences that satisfy some
mathematical deciderator so they should
be consistent they should be unbiased
um they should lead back to Bayesian
inferences under suitable conditions and
and Max and is that thing uh and and we
know uh due to
well work by uh Jane's but but more
recently work by people like Kendall uh
also here at Stony Brook that uh and and
before him
um mathematicians like uh markovichlani
all of this is a large body of work that
points to the idea that if you maximize
entropy you get uh the mechanics of
diffusion so you get the mechanical
rules that generate mass action like um
diffusing particles
excellent I just want to ask about one
word which was unbiased
unbiased mean here
um I'm biased I think you can think of
it as um avoiding overfitting so one of
the things that um you can consider Max
and to be
is a recipe for doing inference that um
maximizes ignorance subject to some
um constraints so if you have some known
unknowns then you want to incorporate
those but if you have unknown unknowns
you don't want to risk overfitting for
those uh things that that you're not
aware of so if you're not aware of
something you don't want to falsely
incorporate it into your inferences and
you could consider this as avoiding
overfitting or you could consider it as
kind of optimizing for subclasses if
you're thinking of probabilistic stuff
as a prob of classification
then you can think of it as optimizing
for subclasses that you don't have
information on but um either way uh it
is the idea that you you don't want to
introduce extraneous information into
your inference because that extraneous
information
biases you in a direction that the data
doesn't support
uh so so that's that's really the idea
behind unbiased and one of the things
that Jane Jane's uh did and not only
James but also
um Shannon uh before him uh who who
worked on the probabilistic aspects of
this
um and then after
um James and Shannon
um
Sharon Johnson who also were uh
probability theorists and and worked on
Max sent axiomatically
um not like James who took it more uh as
a as a physical rule for a long time and
then got into the probability theory of
it
um either way all of these people uh are
able to justify with with rigorous
proofs that maximum entropy is the best
way of making unbiased inferences and
there's there's lots of it to show on
this uh those are are three useful names
but there's a lot more due to you know
Ariel katicia I already mentioned Ken
Dill
um Adam giffum lots of people have taken
an interest in this area uh rightly so I
think
awesome
we're gonna keep moving to now
Quantum and then already many of the
seeds that bring us to Bayesian are
planted so Quantum what is it how did it
come into play in your work yeah um so
quantum mechanics is uh I think
qualitatively different from classical
and statistical physics
uh it's about very small things
uh or very fast things and and as I was
saying effective field Theory tells us
these things usually go together
um
and uh it it talks about kind of when
you get things that are not classical
well at least it started as when you get
things that are not classical what do
you need to add to your theory to make
the right predictions so quantum
mechanics began as a kind of modeling
effort
um
it it grew from what we might call
semi-classical physics which is just
about Quantum corrections to classical
stuff it grew from semi-classical
physics to its own genuine branch of
physics uh in and around the 20s I
suppose the certainly the early 1900s
anyway
um
so one of the things that becomes uh
relevant is
um probability Theory because uh quantum
mechanics
you may have heard about Heisenberg
uncertainty it's about the fact that
measurements do not commute so the order
that you do a measurement in matters a
consequence of this is that there is
always some inherent uncertainty when
you measure
um so-called conjugate variables which
are just things that fit into the theory
as non-commuting pairs so you measure
two non-commuting pairs there is some
uncertainty you can measure one
precisely you can't measure both
precisely and and moreover there's a
trade-off if you measure one with
infinite Precision you know absolutely
nothing about the other one if you try
and play half and half then
um you that's what you get you get um
kind of a blanket uncertainty about both
measurements
um so so because of the uh non-commuting
of variables and and this is kind of an
empirical fact this doesn't come out of
nowhere uh but it is one of those things
where it just happens to be right
because it's so elegant that
um it wouldn't make a lot of sense if it
weren't much like I guess The
Coincidence of synchronization and
Bayesian inference in complex systems
theory
um because uh non-commuting variables
gives us all of the rest of quantum
mechanics
um the the stuff that we really know and
love and also is a
relatively well-defined way of getting
back uh classical physics because all
you have to do is take the theory and
make things commute and then you get
classical physics back
um I'm I'm brushing some difficulties
under the rug it's as you might imagine
it's not that simple and technically it
doesn't work but it sort of does uh and
and if you're interested I guess um you
can look into what's called deformation
quantization which is exactly the idea
that if you take a classical system and
you uh deform it in such a way that
things no longer commute then you get
that quantum physics but um
you you can't really do it the other way
around
uh there's a bit of subtlety to the
other direction
nonetheless uh that is one route to
making Quantum stuff classical stuff
another route is just focusing on the
probabilities so because of this
inherent uncertainty
um Quantum particles they're equations
of motion uh have what we call
transition amplitudes which gives the
probability of moving from one state to
another but but again nothing is certain
in quantum mechanics
if you however uh make it certain
mathematically you can go in and just
take the no noise limit
um more properly you should you should
do something called Wick rotation first
which just allows that limit to make
sense uh although uh well yes yes you
should do that first
um
it you know if you do that you take the
kind of no noise limits then you get
certain State Transitions and this just
gives you back a classical dynamical
system that you know where it's going
once you have the equations of motion
um and and this is the route that I take
in the paper because it fits very nicely
into the path and typical formulation in
a way that kind of just makes things
make sense uh and and one of the nice
things that I then go on to say is
um if you have a parameter sitting
inside that path integral then you can
make sense of why classical physics
comes from the no noise limit by writing
it as a basic mechanical problem you can
write about synchronization and get back
the basic mechanics of classical stuff
just by doing this very well-defined
procedure like this is something that
that already exists in physics and is
fairly uncontroversial
um so so that's that's what you get in
in quantum mechanics it's about small
stuff it's it's fundamentally
probabilistic
um because there is fundamental
uncertainty and and again this traces
back to empirical facts
um
I think that that about covers it I
don't know if I should have said more or
if you uh have other questions that's I
think that's uh
that's sufficient at this Benchmark for
that slide
oh it's great Jacob
yeah um I realized the paper
um dealt mainly with uh Bayesian
Mechanics for classical objects but do
you see Basin mechanics being applied to
non-classical phenomena like Quantum
tunneling or or entanglement uh which
cannot really be explained in the limit
of large numbers and then also uh second
question which is kind of on the
intersection of quantum mechanics and
statistical physics is there any change
in the formalism when you introduce the
notion of indistinguishability between
particles
sure um well those are really good
questions uh I think
yes there is probably an idea
of
um Quantum tunneling that that could be
achieved maybe
um because uh Quantum tunneling if if
you're a physicist this is something
that your um familiar with on the nose
if you're a mathematician this is what
you would think of as an instantum so in
Stanton solutions to the uh equations of
motion of a Quantum field Theory uh um
tunneling Dynamics and so the idea
becomes okay can we describe um
instantane Solutions uh using beta
mechanics and the the answer is I don't
know but it seems like
there is it's it should maybe be
possible because there is at least an
understanding of where points A and B
are if not how to get from A to B but
that that is something that uh would be
interesting to
um
do more work with and and more generally
it would be interesting to think about
uh quantum physics through the Bayesian
mechanical lens
um just because you do get this uh
you do recover this classical limit of
the path integral and morally path
integral quantization should be
equivalent to things like deformation
quantization and geometric quantization
and and other methods even
um and well actually one other one is
worth saying there's a thing called
stochastic quantization which begins
from real valued probabilities and then
makes Quantum stuff out of that and uh
the
Bayesian mechanics as it is construed
today
is very close to stochastic quantization
in a few very key senses so one supposes
it should be possible and
that would be nice
um so that's that's the answer to one
question is uh should be but I don't
know it would be cool as far as um
entanglement and other kinds of uh
information Theory
um
I actually don't know very much about
this Quantum information theory is
something that is relatively new uh and
a lot of people kind of in and adjacent
to
um things like condensed matter Theory
are very interested in this uh but I I
am behind on the literature I think
one of the things that um does kind of
lend itself to information theory in
general is the fact that basic mechanics
has these connections to maxent and
Bayesian inference
and and these are of course ways of
talking about information and
information Theory
um
so
so yes my my thought is something like
entanglement which has inflammation
theoretic undertones uh should also be
possible but again I don't know
um initially
what precisely that would look like
there is some um literature out there
that has to do with the free energy
principle in the context of information
to Theory I am thinking of work due to
uh Carl uh James claysbrook and Chris
Fields they've published a lot of work
in this direction
um which is also something I'm not
totally familiar with uh
but it again it seems like a very rich
area to eventually pursue Connections in
great and then the second question was
about indistinguishability of particles
FM Ali ah yes okay
um
yeah uh so so I suppose you're thinking
of
um passing to these kinds of uh bosonic
the field theories where you just pack a
whole bunch of
um equivalent field States into
um your uh your fox face and see uh if
you can make that make sense
um
I think uh you you may notice this when
we get into the um supersymmetry uh
results is there is a conceptualization
that yes things do change when you
introduce bosonic looking things
um as opposed to fermionic looking
things
um so it does become important to keep
track of the uh statistics of these
particles uh because that that recovers
um things like uh brst charges relating
the two genres of particle and that is
what gets uh the the classical chaos in
the last section
um so there is yes there is a reason to
um distinguish between
uh
the the behavior of the particles in
each Theory uh I think the the precise
nature of that will become clearer once
someone actually uh Knuckles down and
does out Bayesian quantum mechanics uh
where where we'll be able to couple
directly to uh that kind of idea
awesome a lot of fun
topics uh the tunneling do we have to
visit every belief on the way from A to
B
or as it sometimes can seem are we in
one position and then we are in a
different cognitive position
all different kinds of experimenter
experimented questions in cognitive
science even potentially
uh Collective thought
and ways of communication in terms of
these formalisms
yeah and the instant question is is
pretty interesting as well right because
uh it it talks about okay if we have a
system with uh multiple
um classical Minima so if we can if we
can say okay you know uh there are
multiple optimal Bayesian beliefs and
stantons are the uh things that that zip
between those Minima so it's it's a
qualitatively different uh way of
thinking about
um dynamical systems it's it's not a
single Minima and it's not a single
classical trajectory it's multiple
Minima and it's almost like phase
transitions between the two so certainly
that's that's interesting uh from the
point of view of physics excuse me from
physics uh but but tracing it back to
something like cognitive science
thinking about okay what are the sort of
phase transitions between our uh beliefs
um and and can we actually access other
phases right do those in Stanton
Solutions actually exist and do they
describe some kind of zipping between
um maybe generative models or perceptury
regimes or something of that nature it's
very kind of nebulous but
um it's it's a provocative question
excellent Ali
well uh I was in the on the
understanding
that as we go from classical to
statistical and ultimately to Quantum
Mechanics the role of information and
uncertainty in
describing and formulating the Dynamics
and mechanics of the physical systems
um are becoming becomes more explicit
so is it a correct assumption to say
that Bayesian mechanics somehow aims to
put information back in the game and
make it make it equally explicit through
all of those mechanics
yeah absolutely
um I think that's a good way of thinking
about it right the reason why basic
mechanics is so uh General
um much like statistical mechanics is
very general is because it's just about
information and lots of things have
information even at the classical level
we just usually neglect it because we
don't need to think about it
um but it becomes very apparent
uh and and this is part of the
explanatory power of of doing something
like that it becomes very apparent that
classical stuff
um comes about when that information
goes away uh or rather when those
probabilities that uncertainty goes away
that information becomes uh sort of
limitingly large or infinite uh so so
what basic mechanics allows you to do is
actually keep track of how this
information change between these
different scales which is one um
particular uh payoff that I think makes
it very valuable
um but not just bridging scales also
applying to many different scales
because lots of things do have
information information is just a
mathematical apparatus that we can use
to describe lots of things so if that's
if that's all that your physics is built
on then it it will be by consequence
something very general
awesome
the way the it's
coming to me today is in classical
mechanics we get uh especially once we
understand these limits which classical
mechanics is like a point within a
broader space of physics or mechanics
we get principles of least action and
stationarity and laws of large numbers
not unlike the central limit theorem in
statistics and a lot of the esoteric
gaussian statistics
in statistical mechanics the
probabilistic nature becomes
formal
for example in the Billiards case in
classical mechanics you might want to do
statistics across many slightly similar
Billiards games and so at that point you
could either do the plug and chug
frequentive statistics or at some point
you're going to want to think a little
bit more broadly about the distribution
of Billiards
and then Quantum especially makes the
relationality and the modeler models
dialectic formal because just by doing
statistics you're already in an area of
explicit relationality
map territory distinguishing
and then Quantum takes that to another
level
and
could it be said that with Bayesian
we're even going a layer deeper
into the modelers
approach to the system
[Music]
where do you see this yeah so I think so
um
the idea would be eventually we
introduce an actual idea of information
um which naturally kind of depends on
the Observer or the modeler because
information is kind of modeler dependent
right information has a context it has
uh was contingent on observation so when
we start talking about
um surprisal and the Dynamics of beliefs
and inference all of these are very
explicitly putting the modeler back in
the situation and and that may be in the
very metaphorical sense of a system
um synchronizing with its environment it
doesn't necessarily have to be a
cognitive Observer or a uh a pan
psychist kind of modeler I don't really
think there's remit for that within the
maths uh but the the point is that the
maths works with or without those
assumptions so so in a sense it's
actually agnostic to to that and you can
you can conjure an image of uh a modeler
that that is pure metaphor
um just talking about synchronization uh
however the uh the language is pretty
instructive and it does uh relate back
to the idea that that lots of systems
have and can capture information uh
maybe in a very trivial not cognitive
not conscious like sense but nonetheless
uh they do
um capture and and uh
synchronize to information and therefore
they do uh model and they do inference
great it's the classical if a tree falls
the forest does anyone hear it exactly
if a tree falls does it make a noise
yeah I mean I I think the answer would
be
um
it depends on what's synchronizing to
the tree right if the tree falls on okay
this is going to be a pretty Grim
example I guess but if a tree falls on
some sort of small Woodland Critter then
then yes I think the tree definitely
fell because the uh the statistics of
one thing synchronizing to the other one
would say yeah pretty unequivocally
um the tree just fell but if you're not
there you are not synchronizing to the
tree and so that information has uh no
meaning to you whatsoever so so it is
very much about
um as you've written modeler dependent
um information in in a very
mathematically rigorous way
really
um powerful and also connects to a lot
of qualitative and contemporary ideas so
it's really exciting to think about
where and how Daisy mechanics can be
applied
this brings us
um as we head into the z-score of plus
one downhill on the gaussian of the dot
one
into the paper itself
so we'll pause Ali and Jacob if you have
any questions otherwise we're going to
go to the roadmap and have some overview
notes on the paper and its structure
does that sound good
all right
so pardon the meme
but
um here's the road map of the paper the
sections and subsections so maybe just a
general comment what did you include in
the paper what did you not include in
the paper why did you structure it how
you structured it
uh yeah absolutely so uh the the
structure was kind of meant to reflect
um I think an unmet need in the uh
literature which is both
a single place for all of these results
to be reviewed and then uh once that
review has been done an application of
all those results so organize everything
and then use it in a kind of insightful
way
and and having all the rigorous stuff in
the beginning makes the application make
sense and having the application makes
uh or provides context for all the the
very rigorous stuff at the beginning
um so to do that uh it's it's kind of
split almost down the middle
um you have the sections one through
four are all the uh foundational stuff
and then sections five six and seven
are the actual applications
uh so I I began with a very brief
introduction just uh motivating
um precisely this uh here are the
questions that we're going to answer
here's
um how we're going to answer them here's
why it even matters
um in section two I I just very briefly
reviewed classical physics to uh set the
stage for some of the stuff that we've
we've already discussed
um then I uh talk about Bayesian
mechanics itself uh and and to be
through 2D are fairly long because this
sets up all the basic Machinery uh we
begin with um
I I believe to begin with uh we talk
about
um what does it mean for Bayesian
mechanics to be like uh classical
mechanics
um what are the the basics of it
what is variational free energy what is
uh surprisal what is least surprisal
um and then in C and D uh these uh basic
ideas can be used to figure out okay
what does it mean then to minimize
surprisal how does that matter to
Bayesian inference there's exact beliefs
the physics by beliefs is then inverting
the story and talking about okay
um so we know now that uh systems uh
when they minimize their free energy
they uh or minimize their surprisal they
synchronize um to their environment so
you can write this nice story about um
parameters can you do it the other way
around can you begin from the
um no I think I gave them the wrong
direction so when when systems
synchronize they minimize their free
energy so you can read this as Bayesian
inference then I ask okay can you do
this the other way around can you begin
from Bayesian inference and can you get
the Dynamics of parameters which is just
kind of flipping the story but it
involves
um a bit of work to to actually make it
follow through in the end however it
does and and the relationship between
the two so I say physics of beliefs
because one is taking the motion of
parameters and relating to the motion on
uh statistical manifolds uh space in
inference because it's by beliefs to
saying okay if we begin with some
information theoretic idea of Bayesian
inference do we get back the mechanics
of systems carrying those beliefs
that relies on
some work that I did earlier this year
which espoused a kind of Duality between
uh
the free energy principle and maximum
entropy so using that as a kind of
Technology you can flip the story and
say okay if I start from an inferential
principle can I get physical stuff back
whereas the fep is I I would think of it
more as if I start with physical stuff
can I then understand the beliefs they
are two sides of the same coin uh and
uh on the nose it's a very trivial
symmetry between the two
of course it takes a lot more work to
make it uh formally make sense but in
the end it does so that's that's section
two
um section three uh moves us into the
first uh idea of actual results in the
papers to say okay so if I have a
classical system doing Bayesian
inference or approximate based infants
uh what does that look like and does it
look like the free energy principle
um
and then conversely if I have an
inferential principle uh or if I have an
informational physics can I use maxent
as the Dual to the fep to get back the
physical uh mechanics of this classical
object uh and in both cases the answer
is yes and at the end of that section I
uh give an equation that that does
precisely that it takes the idea of mode
matching
um and says okay here is how
probabilities behave when you do mode
matching and conversely uh here is how
uh modes behave when you minimize the
free energy of those probabilities
uh so in in section four I then talk
about okay does this actually make sense
in a physical setting does it tell us
anything insightful or is it just a
tautology that if you build in a
classical mode and then take the limit
to the mode then you get classical
physics if it's if you phrase it just
like that it doesn't seem very
remarkable but um for the reasons that I
described about uh path integrals and
and the classical limit of the path
integral it becomes a little bit more
subtle and so we can actually derive
something kind of interesting uh from
the idea that uh
classical stuff is the mode of quantum
stuff so in the classical limit of
quantum mechanics systems that do
approximate Bayesian inference
exhibit classical physics
that's I think that's really the payoff
of of that section and so it it kind of
justifies the rest of the uh set of
questions that I ask because it becomes
not just a worked example but it does
say something interesting about physics
more broadly I think
uh now we get into the application
section so once that's done
um we we cool off a little bit and we
just do an example of what does it mean
to do mode matching
um this is this is simple enough to
formulate uh and you can see the in this
case the mode so mode matching is about
stationary modes and it makes sense to
talk about the classical physics of
something at rest
um now things that are at rest uh don't
move so uh synchronization uh in this
case is matching a mode to a stationary
environment is when a force is not
acting on you you don't move and this
requires uh
very little maths
um and at the end uh one of Newton's
other laws pops out that objects uh in
motion stay in motion objects at rest
stay at rest
uh
so so you get that back from from
section five
uh from section six you can talk about
modes that move well you can talk about
um systems that move and and there's
actually a finer distinction in there
that I um precipitated uh just saying
which is in in one case you can talk
about
um
A system that moves towards a mode so A
system that tracks a mode but eventually
finishes in a stationary place and you
can also talk about a system that chases
a mode uh so we call this infinite mode
tracking or uh
what you you could think of this as uh
mode chasing you could think of this as
a primitive form of path tracking it's
just the idea that things that go around
in a circle
um you can look at it one of two ways
you can look at it as an object and the
example I use is satellite motion so the
classical physics of
um celestial bodies say one thing
orbiting around another this you can
either talk about this as a mode that is
being
um tracked that is constantly in motion
um so you get infinite mode tracking or
you can talk about this as path tracking
um where
the path is the circular path around the
object and what we track is just that
path and that is what is in 7A so I I
say in 6B you can talk about this
example as infinite mode tracking but
it's kind of ugly it doesn't work very
well
um so this justifies going to path
tracking instead which is a much more
elegant picture conceptually it makes a
lot more sense and
um one of the problems specifically with
6B is that the idea of minimizing the
surprisal of a mode uh becomes kind of
difficult because uh this system is
non-stationary the mode is constantly
moving and so the surprise is constantly
fluctuating but when you talk about the
surprise overpaths it's much easier you
can say okay we are actually genuinely
minimizing the surprise of paths because
we are picking the path of least
surprises
um one thing that I didn't include
in this section
which is possibly interesting and uh
I don't know one of the nice things
about preprints is they are to some
extent living documents so I I could
come back and add this in
um if I was so inclined that in fact I
might
um is the idea of uh moving centers of
mass so path tracking combined with
um some kind of moving frame of
reference
uh the reason why I didn't include this
is because the Maths for that is not
quite worked out yet
but
uh since then
um
uh Lance DeCosta uh and and others uh in
a paper that is probably about to be
released uh it's it's co-authored
between myself Lance DeCosta Carl
friston Thomas Parr Conor Heinz and Greg
pavliatis so uh all of the big
um mathematical Minds behind the last
few years of the fep
um I think I've named all the names if I
forgot anyone then um you'll have to
excuse me uh
they there's some work in that preprint
or their paper that's about to be
pre-printed uh that formulates path
tracking in the context of moving frames
of reference so not just moving modes
along a path but also moving paths
themselves
so one extra kind of layer of
generalization is is now you can talk
about okay what about when the path that
I'm tracking is itself moving uh and and
there is probably the Machinery to
handle that uh in in this paper that's
about to be released uh again it's it's
Lance it's Carl it's Greg Thomas Connor
and myself
uh
so keep an eye out for that um because
there will be something about uh moving
frames of reference in that paper and uh
I may decide to go back and add
something like if I'm if I'm orbiting a
body that is itself in motion so if if
the center of mass that I'm orbiting is
itself orbiting around something else
um what does that look like from the
perspective of the thing in orbit uh
that that's an interesting case
um it's something that I didn't include
uh because it was still uh
that I think there wasn't an elegant way
forward with that now there probably is
um but carrying on
um 7B is is now
um relating
the idea of path tracking so the idea of
a surprise overpass
relating that to the um path integral
approach to uh basic mechanics and
extracting some insights from what it
means to be a path integral and one of
the things that one is allowed to do
in that context is to then develop a
story about classical chaos
and I think
we have um probably some slides later
about that uh that deserves a much
longer conversation uh but but the idea
of that section is to say Okay so we've
done all this arguably pretty trivial
stuff
um now what about interesting systems
like systems that exhibit uh chaos can
we actually describe those things using
basic mechanics and the answer is we can
and it comes out of the pathetical
description in the uh nice way that we
have gestured at with the name g Theory
okay
nice thank you Jacob
um I was waiting to ask this a bit later
on but since you mentioned reference
frames
um I'm wondering
what different sorts of reference frame
Bayesian mechanics deals with especially
in connection to uh recovering classical
mechanics from Bayesian mechanics
the way I understand right now reference
frame is basically imposed by the markup
blanket so when we're talking about the
tree the tree branch performing
inference over over its environment and
being shaken by the the incoming wind
that's from the kind of from the
reference frame of of the tree how would
that be different if we considered a our
own reference frame looking at the
looking at the tree would that could
that still have a formulation within
within Bayesian mechanics and also how
could this relate to multi-agent systems
where we have the classic example that
comes to mind is clock synchronization
where clocks initial pendulum clocks
initially start out of the phase but
over time uh go
um again in in Phase
um I think there's a lot of different
ways to partition that system one clock
is performing inference over the other
but there then maybe we can also treat
it as a as a coupled system altogether
where we consider both at the same time
uh so I'm thinking there may might be
some equivalent of like a non-inertial
reference frame in Bayesian mechanic X
versus an inertial one uh given by the
markup blanket on that specific system
uh so I would be interested to hear your
thoughts on that yeah that's uh also a
good question
um so one of the things that uh you can
begin to talk about in this setting is
that to some extent the precise
placement of a Markov blanket is a bit
arbitrary and this is this kind of
flexibility is actually a good thing
because you do want to be able to Nest
blankets within blankets there's reason
to believe that that kind of multi-scale
um
self-organizing well that that
multi-scale uh patterning behavior that
that multi-scale
um separation and and being able to
infer not only what my neighbors are
doing but being able to infer what the
scale above me is doing
um there's reason to believe that that
is where self-organization comes from
another free energy principle and one of
the reasons to believe that is
um work by uh for instance Mike Levin uh
in the context of the uh kind of
cognitive nature of developing cells
right
um cells that are in a kind of soup of
things uh how do they know
to develop into tissues
there must be some kind of notion of
nested blankets not only knowing what am
I in relation to others but what are we
in relation to a larger scale other
so uh that that's very important
um nesting blankets another really good
example of this is in a paper by uh
Maxwell
um Alec Chance some other people that I
don't remember offhand so I apologize
called neural and phenotypic
representations under the free energy
principle and it's exactly the same sort
of thing if you have a soup
and they know something about themselves
and also something about
something at a higher level
then uh you get self-organization so
it's it's not just about
um
kind of self-organization at the
constituent level but it's knowing
something about the pattern that one is
organizing into uh and and these are two
good examples of that there are lots of
others
uh
so so one imagines you know the the
arbitrariness of the Markov blanket is
important because it allows you to Nest
things more generally it allows you to
change context and you know the the
um context of information is kind of
Observer dependent so
uh in a way you do want to be able to
introduce kind of arbitrary frames
and get different kinds of uh context
for for a given observation set right
you want to be able to reassign self and
other and still get approximate Bayesian
inference
um this is what we would think of as a
gauge Theory it's a symmetry at the
level of the system
that is uh not reflected in the physics
of the system by which I mean you can
make free changes at the level of the
system that don't change the physics of
the system so so in this case it's the
idea that we can change a reference
frame we can change the context of an
inference but it shouldn't change the
idea that systems do approximate
Bayesian inference much in the same way
that we can change the way we label
coordinates in general relativity but it
shouldn't change the idea that
gravitation is the curvature of
space-time in some suitable sense that
has to do with metric tensors that I
won't talk too much about
um
so so something like that is is
absolutely I think not only kind of
useful but it's absolutely essential
um to not only making basic mechanics
make sense it would be kind of
suspicious if inference just fell apart
if you redrew the boundaries
um especially given our conversation
about the uh scale friendliness of the
fep uh it should apply and reapply but
also that application and reapplication
and contextualizing inferences within
inferences is kind of right now what is
reflected in the literature when we
really think about okay how does
self-organization work
um in in these situations uh and and how
does individuation work in these
situations or how are patterns formed
um
and and I think there's there's lots of
work uh in this direction about
um reference frames and the
contextuality of information outside the
ivp as well uh and and I happen to be
familiar with very specific literature
about this in category Theory uh but I'm
sure it's more General than that uh so
you can talk about how does uh context
shape
um an observation
so uh yes I think um yeah on the subject
of reference frames uh and and
synchronization it's important to be
able to redraw uh boundaries so take new
frames of reference and still get
um inference uh in the case of um
synchronizing pendulums you can imagine
okay maybe the pendulums do inference on
each other
um or maybe they do inference on the
kind of if they're on some sort of table
or moving beam maybe they do inference
on the beam and they synchronize with
the beam and therefore they synchronize
with each other that's one frame the
other frame is one kind of looking at
the looking at the rhythmic motions of
the other one and uh and just matching
up like that in both cases you get
inference
um we probably prefer one reference
frame or another
um but but both are in principle uh
mathematically valid even if they tell
kind of different physical stories about
what's being synchronized to
uh and and the example of
um half tracking and a moving frame of
reference is interesting as well because
if you think about
um something like the moon orbiting the
Earth
um
you can you can zoom way out and you can
look at it as the moon spiraling around
the earth as the earth goes around the
Sun but you can also
um pick a reference frame where the
Earth is stationary and the Moon is just
orbiting around the Earth
um so so this is the relativity of
motion right or or if you want to
imagine
um sitting in a train uh it looks like
the outside is moving and you're
stationary
um so so that would be you know mode
matching you're not moving
but from the perspective of the outside
the train has just gone past uh pretty
quickly and you're in the train and so
you're moving you know but from your
perspective you're not so so the
relativity of what is being matched to
is an important consideration
um for for those reasons just to produce
a consistent Theory we have to
acknowledge that we can freely assign
these inferences
um the the important aspect is that we
get the same inferences back or at least
we get inference you know they might not
be the same inferences if you wrote them
down they might be in different
coordinates so to speak but at the end
of the day you should still get Bayesian
inference
um now I don't remember your second
question so you'll have to ask it again
um
I'm actually not aware if there was a
second question but I do have a
follow-up question to uh oh of your
answer uh since you since you mentioned
nested
um Markov blankets
um
I I'm just wondering whether in the
formalism of Bayesian mechanics we can
also admit a kind of Dynamics on the
topological structure of the mark of the
blanket itself because in the case of
cells forming other layers uh
in intuitively it seems to me that it's
a kind of discrete way of thinking about
how we're adding an extra layer of the
Markov blanket and maybe the Markov
blanket initially admits uh some uh
there are some non-integer uh index
connecting to your uh prior work on the
weak Mark of blankets and then it
evolves over time to to form into uh uh
actually statistically significant
Markov blanket but perhaps there might
be also a way for
having just one mark of blanket that
evolves through time and that might also
change
the inferences so uh I'm wondering
whether
uh mechanics uh whether the Dynamics of
particular blankets can also be uh taken
into account in the path tracking
formulation or any other one within
approximate Bayesian inference
yeah um so there are a couple of
interesting things there
um for one thing
uh the the idea that
um perspective matters the idea that you
pick a reference frame and carve up your
environment that way
um does kind of go back to this question
of how do we understand
um blankets forming uh in developing
cells say and and the idea would be that
you know blankets have characteristic
scales right the reason why we see
um something like a stone in nature and
not a lattice of crystalline molecules
is because at our level of observation
the
um the blankets that allow these
molecules to be self-organized is
um completely meaningless but but what
is interesting to our level of
observation our kind of canonical
reference frame is the stone
itself uh the blanket around the stone
itself it's the Stone's blanket it's not
the blankets that
um make the molecules that make the
stone
so
um yeah you know eventually we would
want a much more complete theory of
individuation that covers not just
um dynamical blankets but nested
blankets and uh blankets with
perspective and um and things of that
nature uh the the perspective based idea
is is an interesting one to me because
it allows you to talk about
um things like sparse coupling at
certain levels and and if we acknowledge
that the Markov blanket is coming to a
blanket store in the area exactly if we
acknowledge that the blanket is somewhat
arbitrary then we're free to say that
um any system with enough couplings has
a blanket at some scale because uh the
kind of multi-scale systems in physics
that we're interested in at some scale
are sparsely coupled
um probably not every scale
and
um certainly within a blanket there's
not sparse coupling given a particular
reference frame because given a
particular ref given the reference frame
of myself looking at the stone looking
at the Stone's blanket within that
blanket
I would want to see the stones molecules
cohere in a way that is um not sparsely
coupled right otherwise I wouldn't see
things but then at the level of the
stone it is sparsely coupled so so this
kind of arbitrariness
um allows us to actually do the carving
up in a very interesting way as for a
dynamical systems perspectives on um
Markov blankets I think this is also
possible
um I am working on something right now
that that takes the whole story about uh
physical boundaries
and conditional Independence and write
it in terms of random variables so you
have a whole Suite of possible blanket
States and you can look at blankets kind
of flickering on and off
um or uh
blankets that occupy different states
over time
um this is not nested yet but uh it's
it's one step towards that direction
where you can think about how the
blanket at a higher level turns on or
off given the Dynamics of its
constituents whether they're cohering or
not
um
so yeah maybe that answers your question
this is a great topic to chill on for a
few more minutes
in our final bit of the dot one there's
really a lot here I'll just give a few
dots and then Ali happy to hear your
perspective as well
um you even discussed it as scale
friendly but it's almost like a one and
a half layer model
and that is actually uh preceded by even
simple Bayesian hidden state observed
variable distinctions expectation
maximization just partially observable
Bayesian models in general under an
interpretation where observables are
happening at a given scale of a system
of interest and a hidden phenomena or a
hidden cause is at a higher level of
organization connects these sort of
multi-scale systems approach with a
self-organization approach and we've
talked many times about that lateral and
the vertical there's the nest mates
interacting laterally and then there's
the real or as if Colony level
organization
another point I think it's really
interesting to pull out and explore is
you discussed how important it is to be
able to redraw blankets and still get
inference it made me feel that there has
to be some kind of a locally distributed
local sense making process
such that potentially a vast range of
partitionings can also remain valid like
you can think of different metaphors
there and that potentially the blanket
provides exactly that partitioning
surprise surprise
and then moving towards all these
features
that had been in the uh spectator seats
at the math conference
dynamical nested multi-perspective
systems and the way that some of these
formalisms are pointing towards an
integration
that's
quite far out in some ways yet also may
bring an intuitiveness
to a lot of the ways of talking about
different physical systems including the
physics of cognition and as far as
nature at the joints
perspectives would be one
not the only one but one of those joints
or sparse connectivities or factorized
abilities various ways of thinking about
it but
multiple entities engaging in a
multi-perspectival
multi-scale inference question
it's like two people looking at the boat
they might disagree on how to partition
different parts of the boat or the boat
from the water
but at least their perspectives and
their communication interface with each
other and their observation inference
interfaces with the boat
could be specified
and so then it could be like my map of
me my map of you my map of the boat your
map of you your map of me your map of
the boat and then there's a conversation
with all six of those features instead
of us only looking at the boat and you
did it one way I did it differently and
that's the end of the discussion so I
think it's going to open up degrees of
freedom in perspective
harmonizing
that wouldn't
be classically understood
and that'll be seen as extremely
non-linear and unconventional
behaviors
and it's just yeah we've seen what that
is I agree
um I'll I'll take this opportunity to
point out
um there are other people in the uh
verces lab who are thinking about that
kind of question
um how does collaboration and uh
information synthesis and
um kind of agreement or goal emergence
how all these things fit into Bayesian
mechanics
um so people like Maxwell and uh maholt
are thinking about if I write down
you know these kinds of problems uh is
there a way to talk about agreement as
it emerges through
um you know Collective discussions or
collaboration and it is likely something
um like this it's agreeing on a
reference rate for our Collective
observations and and agreeing on you
know not just sense making but it's
agreeing on how to make sense of
something so there's a kind of two-step
process I learned something figured out
I tell you you have your own um picture
of what this thing looks like we agree
on a picture that uh serves Us best we
we agree on a best reference frame
yes
agreeing on the sense made
is um deciding what to order after the
dish has been cooked does that need to
have a conversation about the recipe and
so many other things
Ali
uh well I I believe this whole argument
around Mark of blankets and especially
the nested Market blanket or the dynamic
nature of them
uh can potentially be connected to
somehow the opposing stances uh one
which is the preformism or
pre-pormationism the other one is uh the
progressive uh differentiation mechanism
which
uh for the in the preformism uh some
people believed that the topology of the
whole state space manifold is completely
pre-formed and we just don't have enough
data to model that accurately modeled
the state space accurately but for The
Advocates of the progressive
differentiation
um Viewpoint they on the other hand
believe that it literally goes I mean
the state space manifold literally goes
undergoes
um lots of Transformations uh according
to uh the
I mean some inflection points or some
singularities and it's not uh pre-formed
at all and the dynamic nature of the
state space manifold is something
inherent to that it's not because of our
lack of enough data to model that so uh
I'm not sure how much you agree with
that viewpoint but yeah that's something
that's yeah I think sure I think the
kind of drawing and redrawing of uh
Markov blankets
um it's probably a point in support of
the idea of progressive differentiation
because uh at one level
um we think of uh drawing and redrawing
as developments
um or uh
oh yes development and and one of the
things that drives development is
something like Fitness pressure so
Fitness uh changes the constraints on
what sort of patterns are available to
you what are you organized into and and
these are not things that we know are
priori at the level of the system it may
be possible that if you write down a
whole kind of a world model of the
entire universe from you know the very
first uh Point uh in time uh
after the big bang or maybe even uh at
the instant at which the singularity
expanded and you had enough
computational power to trace it all
through
uh that you could get to something like
um what is it preformationism
um but that that strikes me quite a lot
as a kind of
um super determinism or determinism
argument it sounds a lot like some kind
of um argument that you know there is no
uncertainty in how you will develop
there is just uncertainty in
um
what you're aware of as to your
development
um or some kind of hidden variables
theory that says there is something
mediating the way your state space looks
you just don't know it and so you have
the illusion of Free Will
um so this becomes a bit of a
philosophical question
um I myself don't really buy into
determinism so I I would be tempted to
say uh that the Markov blanket story
especially Dynamic blankets or however
you want to call them are to do with
Progressive differentiation as we live
our lives we draw and redraw our own
blankets as we mesh and individuate
ourselves from other systems and the
environment and this is something that
we are in control of certainly locally
in the state space we're in control of
it whether there is some hidden variable
guiding our own actions uh is something
that is
I think strictly speaking a different
question
the nice thing about it is whether it's
true or not it doesn't break the
locality of the Markov blanket
construction so uh we we get this idea
of locally Progressive differentiation
as a Markov blanket and then when we
Zoom way out
um it may be a kind of a different story
but certainly um
yeah locally it works as a this kind of
dynamic process
well we almost got to the paper
this was a awesome discussion so Ali and
Jacob if you would like to have any
closing remarks
uh well I just wanted to say
that
I truly enjoyed our discussion today and
I very much look forward to that too
because I have a bunch of questions that
I didn't have a chance to ask about
some of the sections of the paper so
I I just wanted to thank Dalton for his
time and
uh also for Jacob and Daniel for
organizing these uh extremely fruitful
and useful uh discussion sessions and
live streams so yeah I'm very much
looking forward to the next one
thank you Jakob
yeah uh this was an amazing uh
amazing.one thanks thanks a lot uh
Dalton for all the great answers and
overviews uh
of course uh Ollie and Daniel for doing
bulk of the work on the on the slides
and yeah looking looking forward to the
dot two
Dalton any last thoughts
uh no just uh thank you for having me uh
it I did really enjoy it
um and and thank you of course for all
of the background work that you put in
um it's uh as I said it's very
flattering uh to see
um such detailed uh working through of
my work uh so so thank you for that uh
and I am looking forward to the next
episode
excellent well next week us and anyone
else who'd like to join just get in
touch or submit any questions or topics
so thank you fellow see you later
okay cheers thank you